Finding Aid for Helen Belfield Bates Van Tyne Papers 1846-1971
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Helen Belfield Bates Van Tyne Papers 1846-1971, 1950-1966
Van Tyne, Helen Belfield Bates.
1 oversize folder
2 linear feet
Papers of Helen B. Van Tyne and earlier members of the Belfield family. Civil War papers and family correspondence of Henry H. Belfield, founder of the Chicago Manual Training School; and papers, 1944-1971, of Helen Van Tyne, Ann Arbor, Michigan civic leader and member of the citizens advisory council of the Washtenaw County Juvenile Court, concerning her interest in the problem of juvenile delinquency, the Michigan League for Planned Parenthood, the Michigan Council on Women in Business and Industry, and the James Foster Foundation.
86164 Aa 2; UAm
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Helen Van Tyne (donor no. 715 ) and came to the library largely in 1971.
The collection is open for research.
Helen Belfield Bates was born in 1896 in Ann Arbor, Michigan. Her father, Henry Bates, married her mother, Clara Belfield, in 1894. He served as dean of the University of Michigan Law School from 1910 to 1939.
On September 15, 1933, Helen married Josselyn Van Tyne, curator of birds for the University's Natural History Museum and a professor in the zoology department. Helen Van Tyne was both a scholar and civic activist. She wrote several history-related articles and book reviews in the 1930s, which were published in journals such as the Michigan Alumnus Quarterly Review and the Journal of Modern History.
In the mid-to-late 1940s, Van Tyne began working closely with the American Association of University Women, which eventually led to her interest and involvement in a diverse array of issues affecting women and children. From the late 1940s to the end of the 1960s, Van Tyne was involved with a variety of Ann Arbor area civic organizations: the Michigan Council on Women in Business and Industry, Planned Parenthood, and the James Foster Foundation.
The organization to which Van Tyne devoted greatest time, energy, and intellectual effort was the Citizen's Advisory Council for the Washtenaw County juvenile court system. This organization regularly monitored, analyzed and evaluated the judicial procedures undergone by juvenile offenders and sought a variety of social and legal remedies to improve the process. Van Tyne served as chair of this organization for almost ten years, from about 1955 to 1965. In the course of her involvement with this group, she corresponded and consulted with a diverse group of influential legal, political, and sociological professionals, and studied many facets of the Washtenaw County court system.
Other important aspects of Van Tyne's interests can be seen in this collection. After her husband, Josselyn, died in 1957, she spent twelve years collaborating with his former colleagues and potential publishers to posthumously complete and release the book he had been researching The Fundamentals of Ornithology. This book became an authoritative text in the field and went through many editions.
Helen Van Tyne was involved many social and historical pursuits. Together with the other members of her family, she left an indelible mark on the academic and social landscape of Ann Arbor in the first half of the twentieth century. Helen Bates Van Tyne died in 1971.
The papers of Helen Van Tyne consist of materials relating to two major areas: Mrs. Van Tyne's involvement in various Ann Arbor-area civic organizations from the late 1940s until the late 1960s, and a collection of family papers, photographs, and ephemera, particularly relating to her grandfather, Henry Holmes Belfield (1838-1913). The collection has been divided into three series: Organizational Affiliations, Personal Papers, and Belfield Family Papers.
Subjects:
Belfield, Henry Holmes, 1837-1912.; Birth control.; Chicago Manual Training School.; Citizens Advisory Council of the Washtenaw County Juvenile Court.; Civic leaders--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; James Foster Foundation (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Juvenile delinquency--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Michigan Council on Women in Business and Industry.; Michigan League for Planned Parenthood.; Michigan. Probate Court (Washtenaw County). Juvenile Division.; Social service--Michigan--Societies, etc.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Van Tyne, Helen Belfield Bates.; Women civic leaders--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Belfield family.; Belfield, Henry Holmes, 1837-1912.; Chicago Manual Training School.; Chicago (Ill.)--Buildings, structures, etc.; Dwellings--Illinois--Chicago.; Educational buildings--Illinois--Chicago.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Women.
Contributors:
Belfield, Henry Holmes, 1837-1912.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Portraits.; Tintypes.
- Organizational Affiliations 1944-1971
  The Organizational Affiliations series (1944-1971; 1 linear feet) details Van Tyne's leadership and membership roles within several civic organizations in the Washtenaw County area. The materials in this series reflect Van Tyne's concern with issues of child care, juvenile delinquency, and treatment of juvenile offenders in area court procedures. Administrative papers such as minutes and membership rosters and correspondence related to organizations such as Planned Parenthood, the James Foster Foundation, the Juvenile Court Advisory Council, and the Michigan Council on Women in Business and Industry serve to document Van Tyne's various roles and responsibilities throughout three decades as a civic leader in Ann Arbor.
  - AAUW State Legislation 1947-1948 (Box 1)
  - Council on Women in Business and Industry
    - Administrative 1945-1953 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 1952-1954 (Box 1)
  - Planned Parenthood
    - Administrative 1952-1954 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 1952-1954 (Box 1)
  - James Foster Foundation
    - Administrative
      - 1950-1952 (Box 1)
      - 1952-1955 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 1950-1956 (Box 1)
  - Juvenile Court Advisory Council
    - Newsletters and Reports
      - 1947-1966 (Box 1)
      - 1967 (Box 1)
    - Meeting Minutes
      - 1955-1964 (Box 1)
      - 1964-1966 (Box ###)
      - 1966-1968 (Box ###)
    - Miscellaneous Administrative Papers
      - 1946-1960 (Box ###)
      - 1960-1970 (Box ###)
    - Correspondence
      - 1944-1959 (Box ###)
      - 1960-1969 (Box ###)
    - Project 74 1963-1967, 4 folders (Box ###)
      (study made to evaluate services provided by the Juvenile Court)
- Personal Papers 1928-1969
  The Personal Papers series (1928-1969; 0.3 linear ft.) includes a variety of papers that detail Helen Van Tyne's personal and professional career. Included is her correspondence received upon the deaths of her husband, Josselyn Van Tyne, and her mother, Clara Bates. There are also her files detailing the efforts to have published Josselyn Van Tyne's The Fundamentals of Ornithology.
  - Correspondence
    - 1934-1950 (Box 2)
    - 1957, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 1958 (Box 2)
    - 1959 (Box 2)
    - 1960-1967 (Box 2)
  - Josselyn Van Tyne/Publication Correspondence
    - Publication Correspondence 1946-1956 (Box 2)
    - Posthumous Publication Correspondence 1957-1969 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence -- Letters of Condolence 1963, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Miscellanea 1928-1971 (Box 2)
- Belfield Family Papers 1846-1957
  The Belfield Family series (1846-1957; 0.7 linear ft.) includes papers of Henry Holmes Belfield, dating from his service in the Civil War to his position as founder and Director of the Chicago Manual Training School. These papers include Belfield's speeches and addresses, printed materials and articles related to the Manual Training School, several diaries, and other items of interest. This series also includes five folders of photographs of Henry Belfield, his wife and children, and other members of the Belfield and Miller families, dating from the 1860s to the first decade of the twentieth century. The series also includes photos related to the Chicago Manual Training School and the Belfield family home in Chicago.
  - Belfield Family Correspondence 1877-1939 (Box 2)
  - Newspaper clippings concerning Belfield family 1900-1957 (Box 2)
  - Belfield Family Miscellanea 1846-1937 (Box 2)
  - Henry Holmes Belfield Papers
    - Civil War Papers 1863-1866 (Box 2)
    - Diaries and marriage advice book 1865-1910, 5 volumes (Box 2)
    - Chicago Manual Training School 1885-1903 (Box 2)
    - Speeches and Articles 1905-1913 (Box 2)
    - Scrapbooks 1883-1891, 2 volumes (Box 2)
  - Family Photographs, 1860-1913
    (also oversize folder UAm)
    - Henry H. Belfield 1860-1913 (Box 2)
    - Anne Miller Belfield and Children 1869-1871 (Box 2)
    - Other Family Members
      - Male 1860-1913 (Box 2)
      - Female 1860-1891 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous 1860-1913 (Box 2)